Guide to the Patricia Dix Papers MSS 224
Fales Library and Special Collections
Patricia Dix Papers
1940-2001
1986-2001
Fales Library and Special Collections
Dix, Patricia R., 1955-2001 (Patricia Rose)
Arnoldi, Katherine
MSS 224
4 Linear Feet in 4 records cartons
Patricia "Pat" Rose Dix (1955-2001) was a freelance editor and writer in New York City. She was born in Brooklyn, attended Queen Mary College at the University of London, and spent most of her adult life living in Greenwich Village and the Lower East Side in Manhattan. This collection provides a glimpse of life in New York City during the downtown arts scene that emerged in the 1970s through the early 1990s. Materials include resumes; birth, marriage, and naturalization certificates; annotated and handwritten writings; correspondence; sketches; clippings and articles; brochures; utility bills and receipts; postage stamps; flyers; notebooks; day planners; and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Katherine Arnoldi in 2008. The accession number associated with this collection is 2008.224.
Appraisal
Medical records for Patricia Dix and social security information for Patricia Dix and Joan Dix were removed from box 1 folder 34, box 2 folder 9, and box 3 folder 12 for deaccession.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Patricia "Pat" Rose Dix, a freelance editor and writer, was born on December 6, 1955 in Brooklyn, New York. Her parents, Robert Armstrong Dix and Joan Wright Donegan were married at the Church of Transfiguration in 1949 in Manhattan. Her father was born in England and became a naturalized citizen in 1954. Dix attended Queen Mary College at the University of London from 1973 to 1975 where she studied Medieval History.
Dix spent most of her adult life living in Greenwich Village and the Lower East Side of Manhattan. She worked as a caregiver, freelance legal secretary, and freelance editor while working toward her personal goal of becoming a published author. She was an avid correspondent to friends, family, medical and literary professionals, and theater actors. Dix also struggled with health issues that led her to become interested in nutrition and healthy living. She had problems with her lungs and required oxygen therapy. Dix passed away on December 4, 2001, two days before her forty-sixth birthday.
Scope and Contents
This collection provides a glimpse of life in Greenwich Village and the Lower East Side of Manhattan during the downtown arts scene that emerged in the 1970s through the early 1990s. Materials include Dix's professional resume and her friend, Kevin Stevens' resume; Dix's birth certificate, her parents' marriage license and certificate, and her father's birth and naturalization certificates; annotated and handwritten original writings that included sketches; clippings and articles regarding NYC cultural events, book reviews, diseases, nutrition, and healthy living; postage stamps; brochures regarding oxygen therapy; utility bills and receipts; event flyers from downtown literary and theater events; notebooks that contain Dix's personal thoughts and feelings and general notes related to work; day planners; and photographs of unidentified men and women, and a few headshots.
The bulk of the collection includes Dix's writings and correspondence that document her daily life in New York City between 1986 and 2001, and address numerous topics including her personal relationships with men, specifically a man named John; theater; politics and terrorism; cigarettes and smoking; her mother's death; issues she had with people she lived with and their neighbors; frustrations with her writing not being published; working as a caregiver for a woman named Ruth and their daily visits to the Metropolitan Museum of Art; drugs; music; fashion; book reviews; New York Times articles; and her physical and mental health. Dix's most notable writing in the collection is a piece she wrote entitled "Betty Boop: A Feminist Timeline," where Dix describes a fictional account of Betty Boop's life growing up. Much of her writing is present in her correspondence with friends and literary professionals. The majority of correspondence includes letters to and from Dix's friends in England, John and Sue; Teofilo "Teo" R. Ruiz, a Brooklyn College professor she worked with; and letters to medical professionals. Many of Dix's letters to medical professionals were addressed to physicians and expressed her concerns regarding the problems with her lungs and her interactions with doctors and nurses at various medical facilities.
Downtown Collection.; Downtown writers.; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.); Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); Arnoldi, Katherine
- Correspondence to Kevin Stevens, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Resume, event flyer, sketch, 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letters to Dr. Perry, Cher Christain, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Information sheets and articles on nutrition and healthy living, 2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Clippings re NYC cultural events, book reviews, and conformational disease, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letter and email from Robert Whitaker, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letters to Dr. Chawala re Dix's health, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Utility bills and receipts, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letters and clippings, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Letters to Dr. Chawala re Dix's health, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Clippings, brochures, and receipts re politics, health, and oxygen therapy, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Annotated writings, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Personal correspondence, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Educational and vocational planning quiz, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- The Lookout special 1994 annual report issue on seafarer's rights, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Notebook containing personal thoughts and feelings, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Personal correspondence, notes, receipts, 1979-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Annotated writings, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- BAI Scripts [and postcards, photographs], undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Annotated writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Handwritten draft of a play and notes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Personal correspondence with George Trow, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Letters to Patrick and Giani, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Annotated writings and drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Letters to Joanne, Teo, Barbara, and annotated writings, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Clippings - New York Times Book Review, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Annotated writings, notes, Kevin Stevens resume, letters, and play program, 1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Day planner, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Handwritten and annotated writing, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Notebook of letters to Robert, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Letters to John and Robert, and annotated writings, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Annotated book reviews by Pat Dix, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Letters to Sydney, Jim, and John, annotated wrings, notes, 1986-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Letter to Dr. Schwartz, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- "A Sailor's Legacy" notebook, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Photograph of Pat Dix, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Notebooks containing personal thoughts, feelings, and general notes, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Letters out 1987 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Letter to John and Sue, annotated writings re roommates and a sausage ad campaign, 1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Letters out 1999, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Day planner, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Pagen Papers God's Own Drug, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Obscure, violent, funny news items [and script for "The Great Smudge"], 1975-1987 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Letters and writings, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Notebook containing personal thoughts and feelings, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
- "The Icecream Cometh" playbill and Kitting Factory event flyer, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Letters and writings, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Arab Post, published in NYC, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Sailors [letters and annotated writings], 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
- Legal pad with writing about John and luggage tag, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence with Teofilo R. Ruiz and a letter to John and Sue, 1986-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Letters to Sidney Smith, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Letters to Margot, Michael Yawney, Rosa Ruiz, Wes, Dr. Lloyd DeMause; writing fragments, 1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Critics/pedagogy, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Recent U.S. History, 1990-1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- NYC Tarot cards, photo of woman with stuffed panda, clipping, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Utility bills, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Letters, report cards, sketches, photograph of a woman on a bench, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Empty buffalo nickel case, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Handwritten letters, 2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Notebook with handwritten letters, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Writings, notes, study of values test booklet, letters, employment info, 1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Clippings, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Letters, writings, and notes, 1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Annotated folder with letters, notes, resumes, clippings, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Letters, writings, annotated folder, the Writer's Center mailing, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Austin John Marshall book review and interview draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Letters to Laura Flanders, Mary Ellen Keane, Buddy, and a Persona time card, 1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Patricia Dix resume and birth certificate; Robert Dix naturalization and birth certificates; Robert and Joan Dix marriage licence and certificate, 1949-1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Writings, mail, flyers, notes, sketches, 1983-1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Writings, notes, flyers, utility bills, notice of Marshal's Legal Possession of property, 1987-1991 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Letters to John and Sue, Wes, Betsy, Robert, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Letters: Teo, others (personal), 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Teo, pre-1987, 1964-1986 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Sketches and writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Notebooks and writings, 1999-2001 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Writings, sketches, and letters to Mr. Vidal, Mr. Lopate, Damien, Dorothy, Teo, 1987-1998 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Legal pad with notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Exploitation 1 [letters to Ted and Rob], 1995 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Misc. Letters [to Teo, Mr. Cockburn, Mr. Vidal, Mr. Veder], 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Misc. Letters #1 [to Teo], 1996 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Misc. essay topics #2 [letters to Patrick, Teo, Mr. Hitchens], 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Reviews misc. [letter to John and Sue], undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Hello You [letters to Mr. Danes and Ray, notes, writings], 1996, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
- G. Vidal; leftist novelist correspondence, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Exploitation 2 [letters to Teo, Sue and John, Aunt Pauline, Barbara], 1996 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Danny Boy [letters to Pierce Teo, Giani], 1996 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Betty Boop, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Terrorism (public service announcements), 1985-1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
- REI [notebook with writings in French], undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Correspondence, clippings, writings, notes, 1970-1997, undated (Box 2, Folder 42, Box 3, Folder 1-3)
- Letters to Matthew, Monica, Dorothy, Rosemary, Teo, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Kafka [from accordion file in box 3, folder 11], 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- TV Obsession [from accordion file in box 3 folder 11], 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Misc. Literary corresp. [from accordion file in box 3 folder 11], 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Wisker [from accordion file in box e folder 11], 1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Who or what is Edward Meese [from accordion file in box 3 folder 11], 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Brian [from accordion file in box 3 folder 11], undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Accordion file with subject headings, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Letters re physical health, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Letters re physical health and the psychiatric profession, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Letters of grievance, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Letters to friends and medical professionals, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
- Letters, writing fragments, sketch pad, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 17)